"Onions Put to the Test for Weight Loss,
Cholesterol, and PCOS Treatment"
In my last video on onions,
I talked about the data supporting —
or not supporting — the role of onions
in boosting testosterone
in men, protecting bone health,
controlling allergies, and dealing
with chemo side effects.
What about weight loss?
Enter "The Effect of Steamed Onion
Consumption on Body Fat
in Overweight Subjects."
The researchers used steamed onions
so they could better disguise it
against placebo, and dried it into
an onion powder, and gave people
just a minuscule amount, about
an eighth of a teaspoon a day.
Surely, a little daily dusting of onion
powder isn't going to affect the course
of people's weight, but check out
these results reported in the abstract:
a significant reduction in body fat
mass on both DEXA scan
and measured by CT scan —
a significant decrease in the areas
of whole fat, visceral fat,
and subcutaneous fat.
Hold on. If a little onion powder
is so effective for weight loss,
why wasn't it featured in my
book "How Not to Diet?"
Because, as so often happens
in studies, the spin in the abstract
doesn't accurately represent
the actual data.
Here are the DEXA scan results.
No significant change of fat in the
group that got the placebo capsules;
they only appeared to lose
about a spoonful of fat.
Whereas the group unknowingly taking
an eighth of a teaspoon of onion powder
stuffed into capsules lost nearly
one and a half pounds of body fat,
a significant drop from baseline,
but not a statistically significant drop
compared to the placebo group,
meaning the loss could very
well have been due to chance.
Same thing with the CT scan results:
five times more loss of overall fat,
and 30 times more loss of
the dangerous visceral fat,
but did not reach statistical
significance compared to placebo.
A more recent study tried four
teaspoons of onion powder a day
and similarly failed to
accelerate the loss of body fat
compared to placebo,
but the placebo was also
four teaspoons of
onion powder a day.
They used yellow onions versus white
onions, and it seems they both may
have caused a loss of body fat, without
a significant difference between them.
Either way, you can look at these
two studies and say, yeah,
but what are the downsides?
I mean just an eighth teaspoon of onion
powder a day. Why not give it a try?
Can't hurt, but we just
don't have confidence
that it's actually going to help.
Turning now to polycystic ovary syndrome,
also known as P.C.O.S., or PCOS.
It's one of the most common hormone
disorders, affecting 5% to 10%
of reproductive-aged women. In addition
to symptoms like irregular periods,
PCOS is also a pre-diabetic state
with decreased insulin sensitivity.
PCOS treatment is a big challenge
due to medication side effects.
So what about using dietary options?
How about a randomized controlled
clinical trial of raw red onion intake?
Why onions? Well, onion extracts
evidently help in diabetic rats,
and more importantly
in diabetic humans,
but evidently not in
non-diabetic humans.
PCOS sufferers are kind of pre-diabetic,
so would it work for them?
First, let's look at those
other two studies.
Here's the diabetic one on the "Metabolic
Effects of Onion and Green Beans."
Diabetics spent a week eating
either a small onion a day,
or the same diet with about five
cups of green beans instead,
and they both worked.
The onion group dropped people's
blood sugars by about 10%,
and the green beans more like 15%.
Here's the study that supposedly shows
no blood sugar benefits for non-diabetics.
It's true, onions don't lower normal
blood sugars, which is a good thing,
but check out what happens
when you feed people sugar.
Have people down about two tablespoons
of corn syrup, and their blood sugars
shoot up over the next two hours before
their body's able to tamp it back down.
But give people the exact same amount
of sugar, but with more and more onion,
and the blood sugar spike
is significantly dampened,
almost as much as if you had instead
given them an antidiabetic drug.
And we see the same when you
give people a shot of adrenaline —
with or without onions.
So, are there blood sugar benefits for
diabetics and non-diabetics alike?
No difference was found between
the higher and lower onion groups
of PCOS patients, nor
were there any differences
in a marker of inflammation
between the two groups.
But women with PCOS aren't
just at higher risk for diabetes
and inflammation,
but also high cholesterol.
Women with PCOS are
seven times more likely
to have a heart attack, the
number one killer of women,
but raw red onion consumption
appears to be effective
as a cholesterol-lowering food,
though the high onion group
only dropped their LDL cholesterol
about five points, not significantly
different than the low onion group.
I did find this study from nearly 50
years ago where researchers fed
people nearly an entire stick of
butter, and their cholesterol shot up
about 30 points within
hours of consumption,
but only nine points or three points
when combined with about a
third cup of raw or boiled onion,
the moral of the story being
don't eat a stick of butter.